Sissy Themeli

Sissy is a Ph.D. Candidate at the Department of Informatics and Telecommunications (DIT) at the University of Athens (UoA), studying deep learning methods for mining arguments from natural language resources. She holds an M.Sc. in Computer Science from DIT/UoA and a B.Sc. in Management Science and Technology from the Athens University of Economics and Business. Her M.Sc. thesis involved studying various text representations and machine learning algorithms to detect Hate Speech in online content. Additionally, she has experience as a Backend Software Engineer building web services and RESTful APIs, as well as dialog management systems for Omni-Channel Natural Language Interactions. Currently, she is working as a Research Associate at the SKEL Lab of IIT at NCSR Demokritos, participating in EU and national funded projects in the areas of Machine Learning and Natural Language Processing.

Professional Experience

September 2019 - today

September Research Associate, NCSR Demokritos, Athens.

Research at the SKEL Lab of IIT/NCSR Demokritos, developing deep learning models for Argument Mining for EU and domestic research projects in the areas of Deep Learning, Natural Language Processing (DebateLab) and e-infrastructures (DARE project, FAIR4Fusion, etc.).

 Technologies used: Python (data science and machine learning libraries such as PyTorch, pandas, numpy, flairNLP, etc as well as web service frameworks such as flask, django), Kubernetes, Docker, Elasticsearch, etc.

August 2018 -August 2019

August 2018 - **Software Engineer**, *VoiceWeb S.A.*, Athens.

Design and development of speech recognition and NLU/NLP applications. Redesign and implementation of the company products (Dialog Manager and NLI platform) to follow the microservices architecture paradigm. Implementation of various improvements on the application's data layer, creation of a Rule Engine using MongoDB in the backend - the product was parsing XMLs for rule extraction, implementation of a new RESTful Web Service for the Dialog Manager application, redesign and implementation of a new UI from scratch for the NLI platofm product.

 Technologies used included Python, Java, Spring Framework, Spring MVC, RESTful and SOAP web services, Vaadin and others

May 2016 - July

Software Engineer, G.N.T. Information Systems S.A., Athens.

2018

Software development on multiple projects using Java EE/Spring frameworks for backend services(EJB3,Spring Framework, Hibernate, RESTful and SOAP web services), with test-driven approach (JUnit and integration tests). Participation in UI projects written with Vaadin and Android frameworks.

February 2014 -May 2016 Consultant/Business analyst, Deloitte SA, Athens.

Risk analysis, business analytics and accounting/tax consultation services in several company projects. Design and programming of ERP/SAP FI subsystems using Excel VBA in a client's project.

Education

Academic Qualifications

2021-today PhD in Argument Mining, National and Kapodistrian University of Athens, Athens.

2016-2018 **M.Sc.** "Information and Communications Technologies", *National and Kapodistrian University*, Athens, *8.55/10*.

2008-2013 **B.Sc. in Management Science and Technology**, Athens University of Economics and Business, Athens, 7.0/10.

2002–2008 High-School, Lycee Franco-Hellenique Eugene Delacroix, Athens, 18.9/20.

Selected Academic Projects

- *M.Sc. Thesis:* Implementation of a Hate Speech detection framework using different Machine Learning, Deep Learning and text representation approaches. Supervisors: Professor Panagiotis Stamatopoulos (UoA) & Dr. George Giannakopoulos (NCSR Demokritos)
- Big time series and geospatial data analysis, involving feature transformation, learning and clustering techniques.
- Implementation of design patters and multi-threaded applications in Java. Use of aspect oriented programming approaches (AspectJ), C++ memory visualization programs. GC and memory management performance tests on Java and C++
- Design, development and documentation of an Android Airbnb-like application, using MySQL, JPA(Hibernate) and RESTful web services in the backend and Android Framework for the UI

Technical and Language skills

Technical skills

- Programming Languages: Python, Java, R, C/C++
- Frameworks: Django, Flask, Spring, JavaEE (EJB3), Vaadin, Android
- ML & Data Science libraries: PyTorch, Tensorflow/Keras, scikit-learn, transformers, flairNLP, spaCy, numpy, pandas, scipy, Weka
- Testing: JUnit, Arquillian, Spring Integration Tests
- Web services: RESTful, SOAP
- Databases & Search Engines: MySQL, Oracle SQL, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Elasticsearch, Solr
- **Deployment:** Kubernetes, Docker, JBoss/Wildfly, Tomcat/TomEE,
- Build Tools: Maven, Gradle
 Version Control: Git, SVN, CVS
 CI/CD: Jenkins, GitLab CI/CD
- IDE: IntelliJ IDEA, Pycharm, RStudio, Eclipse, Android Studio
- OS: Linux, Windows
- Other: LaTeX, MS Office, JIRA

Language skills

Greek: Native **English:** IELTS, 7/9

French: SORBONNE II, Assez Bien

Conferences and Seminars

- Artificial Intelligence for Multilanguage Services for Citizens and Businesses, ELRC workshop (virtual event, 15/12/2020)
- Using text data to improve causal analyses of electronic health records (speaker: Dr. Aaron Kaufman, place:

- NCSR Demokritos, date: 7/11/2019)
- 20th International Conference on Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text Processing (CICLing2019, place: LaRochelle France, dates: 7-13/04/2019)
- Object-Centric Machine Learning (speaker: Leonidas Guibas, place: Department of Informatics and Telecommunications, date: 5/5/2017)
- The role of relays in the 5G systems (speaker: Vougioukas Dimosthenis, place: Department of Informatics and Telecommunications, date: 26/5/2017)
- Hardware architectures for telecommunication vertices (speaker: Vlassopoulos Nikolaos, place: Department of Informatics and Telecommunications, date: 26/5/2017)
- Human-Centered Entrepreneurship (9th Student Conference of Department of Management Science and Technology DMST, date: 10/5/2012)
- Entrepreneurship, openness and new technologies (8th Student Conference of DMST, date: 12/5/2011)
- Youth Entrepreneurship and digital environment (7th Student Conference of DMST, date 13/5/2010)
- Management science and technology in the modern business environment (6th Student Conference of DMST, date: 7/5/2009)
- Management science, technology and green economy (5th Student Conference of DMST, date: 8/5/2008)

Publications

- Iraklis A. Klampanos, Chrysoula Themeli, Alessandro Spinuso, Rosa Filgueira: "Dare platform: a developerfriendlyand self-optimising workflows-as-a-service framework for e-science on the cloud", 2020, Journal of Open Source Software
- Chrysoula Themeli, George Giannakopoulos, Nikiforos Pittaras: "A study of text representations for Hate Speech Detection", 2019, CICLing